Guide to the St. Mark's Church in-the-Bowery Records 1796-2019 MS 443.9
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Buildings Renovation and Restoration, 1966-2019; 44 Linear feet
  - Subseries IV.A. St. Mark's Church Preservation Youth Project and Other Restoration Records, 1966-2012; 18 Linear feet
    - Files: Publicity; Repairs, 1970s-1999 (Offsite-box 14)
      Publicity files include brochures, newsletters, news articles and clippings, especially regarding the 1978 fire and need for renovations. Files on repairs and renovations include work budgets, work plans, some blueline prints of detail work, contractor/supplier estimates, and some funding requests.
    - Files: Repairs, 1975-1987 (Offsite-box 15)
      These files include proposals, estimates, product brochures, billings, etc. from contractors and suppliers for various aspects of the renovation work (e.g., carpets, chairs, etc., including a new organ and stained glass windows)
    - Files: Funding; Preservation Youth Project, 1969-1993 (Offsite-box 16)
      Includes benefit solicitations, donor support, and insurance claims. Also includes permits, including from the Landmarks Preservation Commission. Much of this box holds records related to PYP participants; those are restricted pending curatorial review.
    - Files: Preservation Youth Project, 1968-1986 (Offsite-box 17)
      Includes files related to the PYP, primarily for the program and work through the mid-1970s (i.e., pre-1978 fire), though there are some documents into the early 1980s. These files primarily concern budgets and workplan proposals for the grounds and church restoration in connection with funding needs. Several files relate to fundraising efforts by the Friends of St. Mark's for the PYP work.
    - Files: Publicity; Repairs, 1966-2008 (Offsite-box 18)
      Publicity files primarily about the Preservation Youth Program; program brochures from the church re-opening and other such celebratory milestone events; files of Landmark Fund budgets, estimates from contractors, and plans for repairs on the church and rectory/Neighborhood Preservation Center (mostly 1990s-2000s); file concerning the graveyard collapse (2006).
    - Files: Repairs; Flag, 1969-2008 (Offsite-box 19)
      Half the box holds a flag made for St. Mark's by Anders Holmquist. the other half holds miscellaneous folders, most of which relate to the Landmark Fund (some trustee minutes and meeting materials) and the rectory renovation and later repairs, including 1997 specifications from the architect Edelman Partnership, use assessments, tenancy, and funding. A few folders from 2006 concern negotiations between St. Mark's and Danspace, and the departure of Reverend Julio Torres.
    - Photographs, 1970s-2003 (Offsite-box 20)
      Includes files of images used in brochures; binder of slides re: graveyards (1976), re-building (1976-86), and stained glass windows (1981-86); envelopes of various photographs and graphics, including photos on church interiors and exteriors and of presentation drawings for the renovation; and a folder of estimates and designs for furniture in the rectory building (2003).
    - Photographs, 1974-2004 (Offsite-box 21)
      Includes slides, many explicitly related to the Preservation Youth Program, though many are unidentified (1974-79). Some slides relate to the Landmark Fund's 25th anniversary presentation and to the Neighborhood Preservation Center.
    - Photographs, 1975-1991 (Offsite-box 22)
      Two carousels of slides re: Preservation Youth Project work.
    - Photographs, 1970s-2001 (Offsite-box 23)
      Includes 4 albums relating to Preservation Youth Project work, the rectory/Neighborhood Preservation Center renovation and opening; and miscellaneous events at St. Mark's, including the ordination of David Garcia.
    - Photographs, 1967-1990 (Offsite-box 24)
      Includes one box of negatives, most identified (1967-82), an album of photographs of church and rectory damage; and images of Hitchcock Presbyterian Church in Scarsdale re: its rebuilding after a fire (1990).
    - Photographs. 4 albums re: Preservation Youth Project, 1970s (Offsite-box 25)
    - Photographs., 1970s-1983 (Offsite-box 26)
      Binders of photographs re: Preservation Youth Project; Various events; Queen Beatrix of Netherlands Visit, "Africa Trip." Also print-outs of images, likely from the slides in the collection.
    - Photographs., 1970s-2001 (Offsite-box 27)
      Album of photographs re: rectory fire & reconstruction, and Neighborhood Preservation Center; miscellaneous contact sheets (1974-81); and a scrapbook of brochures, clippings, etc. (1995-99).
    - Files: Funding, 1980s-2002 (Offsite-box 28)
      Most of the files relate to attempts at funding for the rectory renovation. Includes grant proposals, donations to the Landmark Fund by foundations, financial notes on the Rebuilding Fund, etc. Also includes a report from the architect of an existing conditions survey of the church (2002).
    - Files: Rectory history project, 1990s-2012 (Offsite-box 29)
      Includes binders tracing the history of the rectory and its residents, and photographs and other material re: the Neighborhood Preservation Center.
    - Rectory history project. Oversize, 2012 (Offsite-box 31)
      Oversize boards with historical images for display.
    - Files: St. Mark's historical notes, 1990s-2006 (Offsite-box 30)
      Includes binder of photocopies of correspondence and other documents re: "The Netherlands and St. Mark's" (1981-82) and a binder of "St. Mark's History" with clippings, articles, historical notes, etc.
  - Subseries IV.B. St Mark's Historic Landmark Fund, 1967-2019; 26 Linear feet
    The subseries includes records primarily of the St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund, including those related to its formation, governance (e.g., trustee meeting minutes), fundraising activities (e.g., benefits, solicitations, grant proposals), finances (e.g., financial statements, investment account statements, budgets, Form 990s), and management activities in relation to the restoration of the St. Mark's rectory building and its repurposing as the Neighborhood Preservation Center (NPC), including minutes of the NPC's advisory steering committee. Some files relate to fundraising efforts carried out under the name of the Citizen's Committee to Save St. Mark's.
    With perhaps only minor changes, the files are arranged as delivered to N-YHS.
    - Fundraising, 1978-1999 (Offsite-box 32)
      Includes solicitation letters, proposals, and budgets, primarily to individuals and corporate donors, with some foundations. Bulk dates are the 1980s.
    - Fundraising, 1971-2001 (Offsite-box 33)
      Continues from box 32 above. This box holds primarily foundation fundraising files.
    - Save St. Mark's budgets, financial statements and reports, 1977-1987 (Offsite-box 34)
      Also includes samples of letterhead for the various names used over time for solicitations.
    - Landmark Fund financial matters and governance, 1979-1990 (Offsite-box 35)
      Includes incorporation, by-laws, budgets, reports, financials, trustee minutes, tax exemption status, rectory insurance claims, and some fundraising.
    - Publicity, benefits, trustee minutes and reports, 1979-1999 (Offsite-box 36)
      Benefits include the Peter Stuyvesant Balls (1981-82) and a joint benefit with the Dutch West India House in Amsterdam. Files also on funding and planning for rectory rebuilding, some Fund trustee minutes, and church rededication program material.
    - Budgets, fundraising, trustee minutes, 1988-2001 (Offsite-box 37)
    - Fundraising, Smith Barney accounts (financial), 1989-2010 (Offsite-box 38)
      Includes some rectory rebuilding reports.
    - Financial reports, events, publicity, rectory restoration, 1980s-2002 (Offsite-box 39)
    - Fund investments, Form 990 reports, financial reports, trustee meetings, 1979-2000 (Offsite-box 40)
    - Neighborhood Preservation Center fundraising, budget, proposal, steering committee, legal matters, 1974-2000 (Offsite-box 41)
      Some of the files in this box date to the 1970s-80s and relate to fundraising for the church restoration.
    - Neighborhood Preservation Center fundraising, 1978-2007 (Offsite-box 42)
      Primarily NPC/rectory-related, but also some publicity and arts-related agreements with St. Mark's.
    - Fund by-laws, incorporation, Form 990s; Rectory restoration contracts, supplier/vendor material, publicity, etc., 1979-1999 (Offsite-box 43)
    - Rectory restoration: Preservation Youth Project personnel, daily report logs, budgets, 1988-1993 (Offsite-box 44)
    - Fund trustee minutes and materials, financial statements, 1982-2012 (Offsite-box 45)
    - Fund corporate seal stamps (2); Neighborhood Preservation Center publicity, 1999-2006 (Offsite-box 46)
    - Fund president/officer files, 1990s-2010s (Offsite-box 47)
      Includes various files from Georgia Delano, Stephen Facey, and Nicholas Fish, including trustee minutes, various agreements, concept paper for Neighborhood Preservation Center, advisory/steering committee minutes, etc.
    - Fund trustee and Neighborhood Preservation Center advisory committee minutes and meeting files, 1999-2008 (Offsite-box 48)
    - Five Dutch Days event files, 2004-2011 (Offsite-box 49)
      In addition to the files for the events (a Neighborhood Preservation Center program), there is a corporate seal stamp for the related corporate entity.
    - Five Dutch Days posters (oversize), 2008 (Offsite-box 31)
      Two laminated posters for events on November 14-15, 2008
    - Neighborhood Preservation Center event files, 2001-2016 (Offsite-box 50)
    - Recognitions and awards (oversize), 2004-2014 (Offsite-box 31)
      Includes: mayoral proclamation of October 25, 2004 as "St. Mark's Historic Landmark Fund Day"; certificate, Annual Village Award from Greenwich Village Society for Historic Preservation, 2004; certificate, award for organizational excellence from The Preservation League of New York State, 2014; and symbolic cheque on foam board presented by the Dutch National Fund for Cultural Heritage for restoration of the church archway/gate/fence, 2009.
    - Fund financial records, 1990-2005 (Offsite-box 51)
      Includes form 990s, payroll taxes, audit reports/financial statements, workers compensation/insurance policies, investment account statements.
    - Fund financial records, 2006-2018 (Offsite-box 52)
      Continues from box 51: Includes form 990s, payroll taxes, audit reports/financial statements, workers compensation/insurance policies, investment account statements.
    - Financial transaction records, 2017 (Offsite-box 53)
      Bank deposits, reconcilations, bill payments/Paypal, grant cost shares, Neighborhood Preservation Center billings, office administration
    - Financial transaction records, 2018 (Offsite-box 54)
    - Financial transaction records, 2019 (Offsite-box 55)
      Bank deposits, reconcilations, bill payments/Paypal, grant cost shares, Neighborhood Preservation Center billings, office administration. Some Fund trustee minutes and investment account statements also.
    - Payroll records from Paychex system (RESTRICTED), 2013-2015 (Offsite-box 56)
    - Payroll records from Paychex system (RESTRICTED), 2016-2019 (Offsite-box 57)